<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Multicore on bramp.net</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/tags/multicore/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Multicore on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/tags/multicore/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Performance of Network Protocol Processing on Multi-core Systems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/publications/evaluating-the-performance-of-network-protocol-processing-on-multi-core-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/publications/evaluating-the-performance-of-network-protocol-processing-on-multi-core-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Matthew Faulkner and Andrew Brampton and Stephen Pink&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proceedings of the International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (AINA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This paper won the IEEE Best Paper award&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements at the physical network layer have enabled technologies such as 10 Gigabit Ethernet. Single core end-systems are unable to fully utilise these networks, due to limited clock cycles. Using a Multi-core architecture is one method which increases the number of available cycles, and thus allow networks to be fully utilised. However, using these systems creates a new set of challenges for network protocol processing, for example, deciding how best to utilise many cores for high network performance. This paper examines different ways the cores of a multi-core system can be utilised, and, by experimentation, we show that in an eight core system deciding which cores to use is important. In one test, there was a 40% discrepancy in CPU utilisation depending on which cores were used. This discrepancy results from the resources each core shares, an example being the multi-hierarchy CPU caches, and to which bus the processors are connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/multi-core-networking/AINA-09/aina-09.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>