<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Affinity on bramp.net</title>
    <link>https://blog.bramp.net/tags/affinity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Affinity on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.bramp.net/tags/affinity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>IRQ Affinity on FreeBSD</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2009/03/16/irq-affinity-on-freebsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2009/03/16/irq-affinity-on-freebsd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Linux it is quite simple to set the CPU affinity of a IRQ, by for example issuing the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cat &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; /proc/irq/#/smp_affinity
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will ensure that IRQ # will always fire on core 1. It is also possible to specify affinities such as 3, which pins the IRQ to just core 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be very helpful to stop your IRQ interrupts bouncing between all the cores. For example, if you have a single threaded app which is generating all the network traffic then it makes sense to ensure the network card&amp;#8217;s interrupt will fire on the same core, or at least a core which is close (in terms of cache sharing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I was looking for a way to pin IRQ on FreeBSD, however, it appears FreeBSD 7.1 still doesn&amp;#8217;t support this feature, but FreeBSD-CURRENT does! I don&amp;#8217;t advise people try FreeBSD-CURRENT yet, but when it turns into FreeBSD 8.0, then you can issue a command such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cpuset -l &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; -x irq#
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which will pin the IRQ to core 0, or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cpuset -l 0,1 -x irq#
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which will pin the IRQ to cores 0 and 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this feature will be back ported to FreeBSD 7.X. I&amp;#8217;m a unsure how likely this will be considering there is a chunk of code missing from the 7.X kernel, which I assume will only be in FreeBSD 8.0.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>