<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fork on bramp.net</title>
    <link>https://blog.bramp.net</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fork on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.bramp.net/tags/fork/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The 7 month fork bomb</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2009/11/27/the-7-month-fork-bomb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2009/11/27/the-7-month-fork-bomb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I was helping a student with some C programming, and the remote machine he was compiling and running his code on was running very slowly. It was a shared machine so I assumed some other students were using it. Therefore I had a quick look at &amp;#8220;who&amp;#8221; and found that only one other user was logged in. Then I looked at &amp;#8220;top&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;ps&amp;#8221; and noticed the machine was at 100% load, but I couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out which process was causing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that 7 months ago (in April), two of the students had ran the following code while they were learning about fork:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34; data-lang=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;fork&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each spawned process didn&amp;#8217;t use much CPU, but the system was heavily forking, therefore tying up all the resources. Needless to say I found the two students and gave them a quick slap before asking them to run &amp;#8220;killall blah&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found cool about this was that there was two separate fork bombs going on, and this linux machine was still usable by the other students. Additionally, I&amp;#8217;m surprised that no one in 7 months had actually noticed this! Things were happening so fast that I saw the pid of the forked programs wrap around at least twice during the time I was debugging the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>