<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cdn on bramp.net</title>
    <link>http://bramp.net/blog/tags/cdn/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cdn on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bramp.net/blog/tags/cdn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterising and Exploiting Workloads of Highly Interactive Video-on-Demand</title>
      <link>http://bramp.net/blog/2008/05/20/characterising-and-exploiting-workloads-of-highly-interactive-video-on-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bramp.net/blog/2008/05/20/characterising-and-exploiting-workloads-of-highly-interactive-video-on-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Andrew Brampton, Andrew MacQuire, Michael Fry, Idris A. Rai, Nicholas J. P. Race, Laurent Mathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proceedings of Multimedia Systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a detailed characterisation of user behaviour for a series of interactive video experiments over a 12 month period, in which we served popular sporting and musical content. In addition to generic VCR-like features, our custom-built video-on-demand application provides advanced interactivity features such as bookmarking. The dramatic impact of such functionality on how users consume content is studied and analysed. We discuss in detail how this user behaviour can be exploited by content distributors to improve user experience. Specifically, we study how simple dynamic bookmark placement and interactivity-aware content pre-fetching and replication can reduce the impact of highly interactive media on CDN performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bramp.net/blog/papers/p-brampton.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterising user interactivity for sports video-on-demand</title>
      <link>http://bramp.net/blog/2007/07/01/characterising-user-interactivity-for-sports-video-on-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bramp.net/blog/2007/07/01/characterising-user-interactivity-for-sports-video-on-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Andrew Brampton, Andrew MacQuire, Idris A. Rai, Nicholas J. P. Race, Laurent Mathy, and Michael Fry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proceedings of the International workshop on Network and Operating Systems Support for Digital Audio &amp;amp; Video (NOSSDAV&amp;#8217;07)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a detailed characterisation of user behaviour for a series of interactive sport videos from the 2006 FIFA World Cup. In addition to generic VCR-like features, our custom-built Video-on-Demand architecture enabled us to provide advanced interactivity features such as bookmarking. We illustrate how such functionality may have a dramatic impact on how users consume content. A detailed discussion is also provided on how content distributors may turn this knowledge to their advantage, and thus increase the efficiency of their delivery networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Download][1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]: /papers/p-brampton.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>