<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asus on bramp.net</title>
    <link>https://blog.bramp.net</link>
    <description>Recent content in Asus on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.bramp.net/tags/asus/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>ASUS X56Se Linux</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2008/09/01/asus-x56se-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/post/2008/09/01/asus-x56se-linux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend just purchased a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebuyer.com/product/147001&#34;&gt;ASUS X56Se from eBuyer&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to install Linux on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you google for this laptop you won&amp;#8217;t find many pages about it, in fact I could find no information about the laptop on all of ASUS&amp;#8217;s website. However, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.asus.com/products.aspx?l1=5&amp;amp;l2=74&amp;amp;l3=604&amp;amp;l4=0&amp;amp;model=2109&amp;amp;modelmenu=1&#34;&gt;ASUS M51Se&lt;/a&gt; which looks very similar in the photographs. I&amp;#8217;ve even &lt;a href=&#34;http://vip.asus.com/forum/view.aspx?board_id=3&amp;amp;model=X53Se&amp;amp;id=20080831051338546&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;SLanguage=en-us&#34;&gt;asked on the ASUS forums&lt;/a&gt; if anyone know more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Vista (which was pre-installed) I was able to get this list of hardware, which should help me with the installation process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Atheros L1 Gigabit Ethernet
Intel Wireless 3945ABG
JMicron JMB36X
ATI Mobility Radeon HD 3470
Intel ICH8
Intel(R) 82801HBM/HEM I/O controller hub (ICH8M) SATA Controller
Intel ICH8M Ultra ATA Storage Controller 2850
Realtek HD Audio
Intel(R) GM965 Express Chipset
Intel 82GM965 Memory Controller
Intel(R) 965GM Graphics And Memory Controller Hub(GMCH)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of knowing if Linux would install or not, I went ahead and tried &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.debian.org/devel/debian-installer/&#34;&gt;Debian lenny beta 2&lt;/a&gt;. However, as it was booting it would crash and fill the screen with &amp;#8220;pretty&amp;#8221; colours. I then tried a old Debian disc I had lying around, then a new and old Ubuntu disk, and all these failed to load. So then I tried different kernel options, and eventually I found this command worked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;acpi=off&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it clear, at the Debian boot menu for the installer, you select &amp;#8220;Install&amp;#8221;, but then press tab instead of enter. Then select the 2nd line, press e, and then type the command on the very end. After this press enter, then b to boot the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command disables most power management controls, but at least allows Linux to be installed and boot. Here comes the next problem, X won&amp;#8217;t start. When X attempts to start it again dies either with pretty colours, or with just a full black screen. I haven&amp;#8217;t finished debugging this, but I&amp;#8217;ve tried the Radeon driver, the Radeonhd driver, and the official ATI fglrx.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>