<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vod on bramp.net</title>
    <link>https://blog.bramp.net</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vod on bramp.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.bramp.net/tags/vod/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Case for Hybrid Content Distribution for Interactive Video-on-Demand</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/a-case-for-hybrid-content-distribution-for-interactive-video-on-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/a-case-for-hybrid-content-distribution-for-interactive-video-on-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Andrew MacQuire, Andrew Brampton, Nicholas J. P. Race, Laurent Mathy, Michael Fry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proceedings of Next Generation Mobile Applications, Services and Technologies (NGMAST&amp;rsquo;08)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of numerous video distribution services, Content Distribution Networks (CDNs) are under increasing demand. Given the associated expenses, many organisations have made use of Peer-to-Peer (P2P) approaches to offset bandwidth costs. Unfortunately, using clients as part of the delivery process can vastly increase load on service providers’ networks. Furthermore, many approaches thus far lack the ability for interactive, on-demand viewing. For these reasons, this paper considers how ‘hybrid’ methods could alleviate these issues, through simulations of delivery methodologies in a CDN context. As it is unlikely that any one method will suffice for all content, network and audience types, a successful system should adapt in response to changes, as outlined in this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/NGMAST08/paper.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Download&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/NGMAST08/slides.pdf&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterising and Exploiting Workloads of Highly Interactive Video-on-Demand</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/characterising-and-exploiting-workloads-of-highly-interactive-video-on-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/characterising-and-exploiting-workloads-of-highly-interactive-video-on-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Andrew Brampton, Andrew MacQuire, Michael Fry, Idris A. Rai, Nicholas J. P. Race, Laurent Mathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In journal of Multimedia Systems (2008 Volume 15, Issue 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a detailed characterisation of user behaviour for a series of interactive video experiments over a 12 month period, in which we served popular sporting and musical content. In addition to generic VCR-like features, our custom-built video-on-demand application provides advanced interactivity features such as bookmarking. The dramatic impact of such functionality on how users consume content is studied and analysed. We discuss in detail how this user behaviour can be exploited by content distributors to improve user experience. Specifically, we study how simple dynamic bookmark placement and interactivity-aware content pre-fetching and replication can reduce the impact of highly interactive media on CDN performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/MMSJ/iVOD_MMSJ.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Download&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/tree/master/ivod/MMSJ&#34;&gt;LaTeX Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/poster/Poster.pdf&#34;&gt;Poster&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/tree/master/ivod/poster&#34;&gt;Poster Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterising user interactivity for sports video-on-demand</title>
      <link>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/characterising-user-interactivity-for-sports-video-on-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.bramp.net/publication/characterising-user-interactivity-for-sports-video-on-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Andrew Brampton, Andrew MacQuire, Idris A. Rai, Nicholas J. P. Race, Laurent Mathy, and Michael Fry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proceedings of the International workshop on Network and Operating Systems Support for Digital Audio &amp;amp; Video (NOSSDAV&amp;#8217;07)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a detailed characterisation of user behaviour for a series of interactive sport videos from the 2006 FIFA World Cup. In addition to generic VCR-like features, our custom-built Video-on-Demand architecture enabled us to provide advanced interactivity features such as bookmarking. We illustrate how such functionality may have a dramatic impact on how users consume content. A detailed discussion is also provided on how content distributors may turn this knowledge to their advantage, and thus increase the efficiency of their delivery networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/NOSSDAV07/p-brampton.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Download&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/tree/master/ivod/NOSSDAV07&#34;&gt;LaTeX Source&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/raw/master/ivod/NOSSDAV07-slides/slides.pdf&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bramp/publication/tree/master/ivod/NOSSDAV07-slides&#34;&gt;Slides Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>